Guide to the Peruvian Collection, 1583-1892
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Peruvian Collection, 1583-1892
  - Perú (Viceroyalty). Documentos inéditos., 8
    29. Official letter signed by Viceroy Joaquín de la Pezuela y Sanchez, Marqués de Vilumá, on May 10, 1818, requesting from the Indendente of Huamanga a list of all the military chiefs and officers under his command in that territory. 1 f.
    30. Official letter signed by the General en Jefe del Ejercito del Alto Perú, José de la Serna, on Oct. 20, 1818, addressed to the Presidente del Cuzco ordering the construction of equipment for the army as soon as possible. 1 f.
    31. Royal Cédula signed by King Ferdinand VII on Oct...., 1818, granting the Reales Beneficios to the Province of Cuzco and giving the title of Fidelísima to its capital, the city of Cuzco. 2 ff.
  - Libro de la Razon de Salidas correspondientes a la Contaduria Pral. de los Efectos que se Registran el las Embarcaciones que Salen pare los Reynos de España y Otros Puertos de Esta Mar del Sur en el presente Año de 1774., 9
    Callao, Perú, 1774. 91 pages.
    This original manuscript is a register of goods exported in ships from the port of Callao, Perú, to Spain and other ports of the Southern Sea during 1774. Names of the owners or shippers of the goods, dates of registration, names of the ships, descriptions of the goods, ports of destination, names of the persons to whom the goods are sent, numbers of the invoices and the value of the goods are specified. The first pages include an index by the first name of the shippers. On the last two pages of the volume there is a summary of the invoices included in this book with an estimate of the value of the goods. This manuscript is an important source of information on commerce and shipping in Perú during 1774.
  - Monzón, Pascual Antonio Data de Penas de Camara, su Rezor. Gral. Dn. Pasqual Anto. Monzon. Año de 1777. Data de los Pesos que voy pagando en Virtud de Decretos del Superior Govierno y demas Tribunales a Saver. Desde 1º. de Agosto de 1777. Penas de Camara. Gastos de Justicia., 10
    Lima, 1777-1779. 15 folios.
    Account book of the payments that D. Pasqual Antonio Monzon made from the funds of Penas de Cámara to cover the Gastos de Justicia. Penas de Cámara were the pecuniary penalties or fines imposed by the judges and the courts. These funds were deposited in the Royal Treasury. Gastos de Justicia were the expenditures incurred by the different activities of the Administration of Justice and were paid from the funds of the Penas de Cámara.
    This original manuscript includes the names of the persons who received the payments for services to assist the Administration of Justice and the decrees and sentences that ordered the payments. The records date between Aug., 1777, and Nov., 1779, at Lima, Perú.
  - Florez, Tomás. Prontuario de capellanías fundadas en el Perú., 11
    Perú, 1564-1718. Bound, 1821. [19], 283 folios.
    This volume contains résumés of capellanías in Perú examined since 1680, the year in which the Licenciado Don Francisco de Xauregui was appointed Visitador de Capellanías. The capellanía, or chaplaincy, was capital, the interest of which was required by Spanish law for the support of an ecclesiastic whose duties were to celebrate masses and to perform other pious obligations. The résumés include information about the nature, purposes, and duties imposed by the founders of the capellanías, the persons that possessed them in full right or on an interim basis, and the patrons responsible for the appointments. The capellanías described in this prontuario were founded between 1564 (f. 120) and 1683 (f. 211). Notations added to the original résumés date as late as 1718 (f. 231).
    One of the common watermarks on the paper resembles watermarks illustrated in Edward Heawood,
    Watermarks Mainly of the 17th and 18th Centuries (Hilversum, Holland, 1957), Pl. 114-119.
    These watermarks date between 1665 and 1766, and it is reasonable to assume that this paper was manufactured and used during this period.
    The dates of the capellanías and the notations about them and the dating of the watermarks all indicate that the documents bound in this volume date from the late 17th century and early 18th century.
    This volume was ordered to be bound in 1821 by Presbitero Tomás Florez, Archivero de la Curia Eclesiastica and Colector del Donativo Eclesiastico Voluntario. This event was apparently provoked by changes in the Spanish law that prohibited the foundation of new capellanías and ordered the incorporation of their properties to the government treasury during 1820 and 1821. This legislation was cancelled in 1823.
  - Convenio celebrado entre los generales de los ejércitos titulados nacional y del gobierno de Chile, Mayo 3, 1814., 12
    Lircay River, near Talca, Chile. Copy, ca. 1814. 3 pages.
    The agreement was reached the 3rd of May, 1814, on the banks of the Lircay River near the city of Talca. It was signed by the general in chief of the national army, Brigadier Gabino Gainza and the principal chiefs of the army of the government of Chile, Generals Bernardo O'Higgins and Juan Mackenna. In this agreement Chile offered to send deputies to the Cortes as its representatives, and as an integral part of the Spanish monarchy; to recognize Ferdinand VII as its monarch, and the Regency that approved the Junta of Chile, that will act as interior government with all its power and faculties. Chile would have free commerce with the allied and the neutral nations, especially with Great Britain. The royalist army would evacuate Chilean territory, ending the hostilities; and properties confiscated after February of 1810 would be restored.
    Don José Abascal, Viceroy of Perú, disapproved the agreement and sent to Chile another expedition in July, 1814, that undertook the campaign that ended with the Battle of Rancagua, retaining Chile under Spanish domain till 1824.
    The paper on which the agreement is written was made in Capellades, Catalonia, Spain, by the Almirall family who produced paper there for a long period of time. Three examples of their work are illustrated and discussed in Oriol Valls I Subirà,
    Paper and Watermarks in Catalonia (Amsterdam, 1970), Vol. I, plates 2-3, and Vol. II, p. 238.
    All the examples date during 1804-1824, and those of 1807 and 1809 most closely resemble the watermarks on the manuscript. These facts suggest that the paper on which this copy of the agreement is written and the copy itself are reasonably contemporary with the signing of the agreement in 1814. This copy of the agreement differs from the one published in the second volume of Archivo de don Bernardo O'Higgins (Santiago de Chile, 1947), pp. 156-159. Some words are missing, and others are written with misspellings common in South America during that period, for example the signatures of O'Higgins and Mackenna.
  - Lambayeque. Peru (Dept.) Descripcion geografica, demostrativa y evidente de la ciudad de Lambayeque su cituacion y estencion. Numero de pueblos y havitantes de todo su partido sur cabildos y tribunales, edificios; segun la razon estadistica que se pide, y en que abraza su enumeracion el estado politico y militar el economico civil y eclesiastieo de este partido., 13
    n.p., ca. 1821-1822. [94] pages.
    This manuscript was written to be delivered into the hands of José de San Martin, as is stated in its first page. It is a geographic description of the Department of Lambayeque, Perú. It includes information on towns, population, courts, buildings, and describes the political, military, and ecelesiastieal organizations together with the eeonomie conditions of the department.
    San Martin proclaimed the independence of Perú on July 28, 1821, assuming the title of Protector. He held the protectorship and military command until September, 1822, when he resigned and relinguished power to the new Peruvian Congress. These facts suggest that this description was written during the period of the protectorship and is either an original or a copy contemporary with the years 1821-1822.
  - Apuntamientos de novedades, 14
    v. p., 1700-1702. Folios 372-378.
    Manuscripts concerned with the succession of Charles II, King of Spain, by Philip V, Madrid, March 20, 1702, ff. 372-373. News received at the Port of Buenos Aires from San Gabriel Island, signed by Bartolomé Montellano, n. d., f. 374. Copies of two letters from the Governor of Havana addressed to General Mascarau, dated on April 29, and on May 6, 1700, ff. 375-376. Two additional reports related to the same period, n. d., ff. 377-378.
  - Viage que hicieron á Manoa los RR. PP. Fray Manuel Gil, Comisionado de las Misiones Seráficas, Fray Valentín Arrieta Misionero Apostolico y Francisco de Josef, Guardian actual del Colegio Fide de Santa Rosa de Opoca. año de 1767., 15
    n.p. copy, ca. 1767. [6] folios.
    Fr. Manuel Gil was the leader of this Franciscan missionary expedition to Manoa in El Dorado territory where the Indians were revolting during the year 1767. He had a name similar to the eminent Jesuit mathematician and physicist Manuel Gervasio Gil (1745-1807), who, according to information from
    Enciclopedia Universal Ilustrada (Espasa-Calpe, S.A., Madrid, 1925) Vol. XXVI, p. 34,
    was at Río de la Plata and was expelled together with other Jesuits to Italy during 1767. Considering the distance between Lima and Río de la Plata and the fact that one was a Franciscan and the other a Jesuit, it is difficult to believe that it was the same person. The information about the Indians' revolt in Manoa and the difficulties suffered by the members of the missionary expedition, including a list of the missionaries and Christian Indians killed during the revolt make this manuscript copy an important one (see folio [6]).
  - Pérignon, Dominique Catherine de (1754-1818). Memoria presentada por el Embajador de Francia al Excmo. Sr. Príncipe de la Paz. Madrid, 25 de Abril de 1797., 16
    Madrid, Spain, 1797. Copy, [2] folios.
    Manuscript copy of the memorandum sent to Manuel Godoy (1767-1851), Prince of the Peace, and Prime Minister of Spain, on April 25, 1797, by Dominique Catherine de Pérignon (1754-1818), French Ambassador in Spain. Contains an inquiry relative to a naval engagement between English and Spanish warships, and expresses the opinion of the French Directory censuring the conduct of the Spanish warships for not fighting the English warships during that naval engagement, and requesting the punishment of those responsible.
    Followed by: Diario de Montevideo, containing news gathered from ships that put in at the Port of Montevideo from June 30 to July 11, 1797. Includes information about the more important events in Europe and in other Spanish colonies during the previous months, with a report about the ships arriving at and departing from that port during those days.
  - Andrade, Marcos de. Copia de los inventarios de las alhajas de esta Santa Iglesia Metropolitana de los Reyes. 20 de enero de 1797., 17
    Lima, Perú, 1797. [11] folios.
    Manuscript copy of the inventories of the church property in the Santa Iglesia Metropolitana de los Reyes at Lima, Perú, on Jan. 20, 1797. It includes: sacred vestments, engraved silver, relics, linen, images, bells, books of anthems, precious stones set in gold or silver, and goods and ornaments of the chapels of Santa Ana and Santa Isabel in that church. There is a note at the end explaining that the inventory of the goods and ornaments of the altar of Nuestra Señora de la Antigua is not included because they are the property of the University of San Marcos. The University uses that altar to deliver the major degrees in public ceremony. The inventories were finished on Jan. 20, 1797, and signed by Marcos de Andrade.
  - Perú. Ministerio de Hacienda Cuaderno 2º de oficios y consultas que empezó a correr el año de 1825., 18
    Lima, Perú, 1825-1826. 35 folios.
    This original manuscript is a memorandum book of the General Treasury of the Ministry of Finance of Perú. It contains copies of: official letters, proposals from the General Treasury to the Minister of Finance related to state properties ordering their sequestration from the tenants for not paying the rent, a report of the salaries of the staff of the General Treasury, and other proposals related to business to be solved by that ministry between April 22, 1825, and January 17, 1826.
  - Alvarez Morán, Antonio. Libro de cuentas correspondiente a la general que el albacea lleva con la testamentaría del finado D. Antonio Alvarez Morán desde 4 de Julio de 1820., 19
    Lima, Perú, 1820-1823. 21 folios.
    This original manuscript is one of the account books of the general account of the testamentary execution of the estate of the late Don Antonio Alvarez Morán, carried out by the testamentary executor Don Francisco Valerio Gassols. This volume includes different accounts: one for the amount received according to the inventory; one for the amount collected from rents and sales; and another account for the value of the jewels, slaves, engraved silver, furniture, vehicles for transporting persons or goods, and animals in the possession of the widow. At the end is a list of the goods that were in the possession of the testamentary executor including the amount of 29,815 pesos and 4 1/2 reales given as a stipend for his labor on March 31, 1823. It is followed by a list of the debts of the estate of the late Don Antonion Alvarez Morán.
  - Solís y Rivadeneyra, Antonio de, 1610-1686. Obras líricas de Don Antonio de Solís., 20
    Copy, n. d. 94 pages
    The undated original of this typescript is contained in a volume of Manuscritos varios at the Archivo Nacional del Perú. There are 104 poems written in serveral forms, including sonnets and ballads.
    Solís, a Spanish dramatist and historian, studied law at Salamanca, and in 1654 was appointed Secretary of State as well as Private Secretary to Philip IV of Spain. Later he obtained the lucrative post of Chronicler of the Indies. His Historia de la Conquista de Méjico, deservedly ranks as a Spanish prose classic. It was published in 1684; an English translation by Townshend appeared in 1724.
  - San Román, Miguel de, Pres. Perú. (1802-1863) Mensaje del Presidente de la República al Congreso Extraordinario de 1863., 21
    Lima, Perú, Feb. 5, 1863. 3 pages.
    Typewritten copy of the message sent to the Extraordinary Congress of 1863 by Miguel de San Román, President of Perú, together with the budget proposal submitted to that Congress for its approval on Feb. 5, 1863. President San Román died on April 3, 1863, less than two months after the date of this message.
  - Castilla, Ramón, Pres. Perú (1797-1867) Discurso del Presidente de la República, al cerrar las sesiones del Congreso Extraordinario de 1850., 22
    Lima, Perú, March 26, 1850. 24 pages.
    Manuscript copy of the speech delivered by Ramón Castilla, President of Perú, to the last session of the 1850 Extraordinary Congress, on March 26 of the same year. It is a report of his government in the last five years (1845-1850), and an acknowledgement to the Congress of its collaboration. After Perú became a Republic in 1820, Castilla was the first president to complete his first term in government without an insurrection against him. He is considered by historians the most influential political figure in Perú during the 19th century.
  - Zevallos, Mariano H. Mensaje de S. E. el Primer Vice-Presidente de la República., 23
    Lima, Perú, July 28, 1872. 4 pages.
    Typewritten copy of the message sent to the Congress by Mariano H. Zevallos, First Vice-President of Perú, when by constitutional mandate he became President of Perú following the assassination of President José Balta Montero (1814-1872). President Balta was murdered on July 26, 1872, one week before the end of his term of office.
  - Valle y Caviedes, Juán del, 1652-1692. Caviedes. Colección de sus poesías., 24
    Siglo XVII. 289 ff.
    Juán del Valle y Caviedes was the first satirical poet in Perú.
    According to the typed memorandum of F. Pérez de Velasco, dated Lima, March 26, 1908, that is in the front of this volume, Ricardo Palma brought out a later edition of the poetry of Juán del Valle y Caviedes based on a manuscript copy from the library of Cipriano Coronel Zegarra. The manuscript copy, here in the Peruvian Collection, written at the second half of the 17th century, of the poems of Caviedes was very useful for correcting errors in the copies published by Ricardo Palma. It includes more than sixty unpublished sonnets and many other unedited poems of Caviedes. Copies of his poems are preceded by an incomplete poem of an unknown author. The table of contents is incomplete, but there are two typed copies that include all the titles of the poems in the manuscript.
    According to a bibliographical note of the Peruvian literary historian Rubén Vargas Ugarte on page xxi of vol. I of his collection Clasicos Peruanos entitled
    Obras de Don Juán del Valle y Caviedes (Lima, 1947)
    , this is the oldest ant complete manuscript consulted, and he used it as a guide for the compilation of the complete works of the poet. The watermarks on the paper resemble watermarks illustrated in Edward Heawood,
    Watermarks Mainly of the 17th and 18th Centuries (Hilversum, Holland, 1975), Pl. 114-119
    , used on paper manufactured between 1665 and 1766, and it is reasonable to assume, as Pérez de Velasco did in his typed memorandum, that this manuscript was written at the end of the 17th century.
    Caviedes, known as the riverbank poet, (el poeta de la ribera), revealed in his poems a profound rancor against physicians, but his ingenuous and burlesque versification was simple and unaffected, without any trace of " gongorismo," a lofty style of writing commonly used by poets during that period.
  - Lima (Ecclesiastical Province) Council, 1772. Pareceres que se hen dado sobre los puntos pertenecientes al actual Concilio Provincial celebrado en esta ciudad de los Reyes del Perú., 25
    Años de 1772 a 1773. 1014 pages.
    The Concilio Provincial is an assembly of the clergy of an ecclesiastical province gathered to deliberate upon points of doctrine and discipline of the Catholic religion. The decisions approved by these councils are an important source of canon law in the Catholic Church. This manuscript of more than 1,000 pages contains 49 opinions handed down by the consultants that participated in the Concilio Provincial that took place in Lima, Perú, during 1772-1773. This was the last Concilio that took place in Lima under the Spanish rule. The Archbishopric of Lima was highly interested in obtaining this manuscript from the owners of the Pérez de Velasco collection to whom they made a very substantial offer. This manuscript is an excellent source of information for researchers interested in the study of the history of the Catholic Church in Spanish America, and of the treatment given to the Indians by the Catholic Church during the colonial period.
    The record of proceedings and resolutions of this Concilio were published by Rubén Vargas Ugarte in volume II of
    Concilios Limenses (1551-1772), Lima, 1952.
    The same author published in 1945, Manuscritos Peruanos en las Bibliotecas América in which he describes, in a summary form, the opinions expressed in this manuscript. Also included are the names of the consultants and the subjects treated in the opinions above mentioned. (See pp.237-240).
  - Odriozola, Manuel de (1804-1889). Papeles Varios de la Biblioteca Nacional., 26
    Lima, Perú, 1879. 102 folios.
    Manuscript copies of originals in the Biblioteca Nacional assembled by Odriozola during 1879. There are poetical works by Felipe Pardo Aliaga (1806-1868), Juan del Valle y Caviedes (1652-1692) and by other poets (folios 1-38). Among the prose selections are: Introducción a la historia de los Incas del Perú published in El Mercurio Peruano No. 176, Sept. 9, 1792, (folios 39-45); Ejecucion de la pena de muerte impuesta al asesino del General Sucre, copy of the original printed in Bogotá, Nov. 30, 1842 (folios 45-49); Diversas noticias historicas. Los Portugueses y la Inquisición (folios 49-52); Gigantes, (folio 52); Enigma, poem, (folio 53); Volcán de Ubinas, (folios 53-54); Monstruo, (folio 54); Civilización Ratuna published in El Instructor Peruano, (folio 55); Ruina de Pasto published in El Nacional, Caracas (folios 55-56); El Baile de los Mostrencos, poem, (folios 56-57); ¡Hoy trace un año! En el Aniversario de las matanzas de Arequipa del 25 de Noviembre de 1849, poem (folios 58-60); A la Paz, poem (folio 60); Soneto, Decima and Estrofa suelta, poems (folio 61); José Marla de Cordova y Urrutia, Restablecimiento de los Archivos destruidos pare former una exacta historia del Perú, published in El Comercio Nos. 2,796 and 2,800, Oct. 25 and 27, 1848. (folios 61-66); Haciendas o fundos rústicos que en el Perú pertenecieron á los Jesuítas y que fueron vendidas durante los ocho primeros años despuesde la expulsion (folios 66-67); Fundación de la Iglesia y Convento de la Compañía de Jesús que se arruinó en la inundacion del mar en el Callao á cause del terremoto del 28 de Octubre de 1746 copied by Odriozola from an unfinished chronicle of the Society of Jesus dated 1651-1653 at the National Library in Lima, March 26, 1879 (folios 68-91); Carte annua de 1639 del Provincial de la Sociedad de la Companía de Jesús del Colegio de San Pablo de Lima al General de dicha Compañía en Roma detallandole el estreno del Nuevo Templo de San Pablo, conocido troy por San Pedro, verificado el 31 de Julio de 1638 (folios 92-94); Ceremonial en el recibimiento de los Virreyes, signed at Lima on June 25, 1747, by Alvaro Navia Bolaños y Moscoso and copied by Odriozola from the original at the National Library on Oct. 14, 1879 (folios 95-101); followed by a newspaper clipping of a poem titled No hay que precipitarse published in El Nacional on March 7, 1879. Odriozola finished assembling this volume on Oct. 14, 1879.
  - Cordova y Urrutia, José Maria de. Restablecimiento de los archives destruídos pare former una exacta historia del Perú., 27
    Lima, Perú, 1848. 16 pages. copy.
    Manuscript copy of articles published in El Comercio, Nos. 2796 and 2800 on Oct. 25 and 27, 1848, recommending the restoration of the Peruvian archives. This manuscript copy is exactly the same as the one in MS. 26, folios 61-66.
  - Odriozola, Manuel de (1804-1889). Colección de documentos históricos. Cuaderno 3., 28
    Lima, Perú. 1860. 93 folios. Index.
    This volume contains manuscript copies and newspaper clippings assembled by Odriozola chiefly of poems and essays published in the Peruvian newspapers El Telegrafo, El Pacificador del Perú, and El Mercurio Peruano after Perú became a republic in 1820. Most of the poems were written by the Peruvian satirical poet José Joaquín Larriva (1780-1832). The newspaper clippings include: a Memoria about the Chilean National Navy read at the University of Chile by Don Antonio Garcia Reyes on Oct. 11, 1846; a royal cédula of Sept. 15, 1802, granting royal priviledges to the city of Lima; a biography of General José de San Martin; a letter from San Martin to Bolivar granting him the direction of the war in Perú; and a Letrilla of the Peruvian poet and politician Felipe Pardo y Aliaga (1806-1868). Odriozola assembled this volume between July 27, 1855, and June 1, 1859. An index is included at the end of the volume.
  - García Moreno, Gabriel (1821-1875) Adiós a García Moreno., 29
    Guayaquil, Ecuador. June 26, 1866. Printed broadside. 2 copies.